<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>

<TEI xml:id="noble-deeds.1836.001.xml" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Noble Deeds of Woman.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <date>2019</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>This file is freely distributed and licensed under a Creative Commons
                        Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">This file was produced for English 478/878: Digital Archives
                    and Editions, Department of English, University of Nebraska-Lincoln, Spring
                    2019.</note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title level="a">Noble Deeds of Woman.</title>
                    <publisher>Carey, Lea, and Blanchard.</publisher>
                    <date when="1836">1836</date>
                    <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
                    <biblScope unit="chapter">Filial Affection</biblScope>
                    <biblScope unit="page">27-52</biblScope>
                    <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                    <note>Transcribed from Rare Books, Archives &amp; Special Collections,
                        University Libraries, University of Nebraska-Lincoln. </note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p/>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <listPerson type="referenced">
                    <person/>
                </listPerson>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2019-03-13"><name>Ashley Morrison</name> added settlement tag</change>
            <change when="2019-02-28"><name>Ashley Morrison</name> proof-read document</change>
            <change when="2019-02-27"><name>Ashley Morrison</name> create TEI/XML document</change>
            <change when="2019-02-26"><name>Paige McCoy</name> create OCR of Filial Affection
                chapter and proof-read OCR</change>
            <change when="2019-02-26"><name>Phillip Howells</name> cropped &amp; editted
                images</change>
            <change when="2019-02-12"><name>Paige McCoy</name>, <name>Ashley Morrison</name>, &amp;
                    <name>Phillip Howells</name> Created TEI Header</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="chapter">
                <pb facs="noble_028.jpg" n="27"/>
                <fw>39</fw>
                <head>F<hi rend="smallCaps">ilial</hi> A<hi rend="smallCaps">ffection</hi>.</head>
                <lb type="horBar"/>
                <p>ROMAN DAUGHTER.—XANTIPPE.—MARGARET ROPER.— MRS. MORICE.—AMERICAN DAUGHTER.—
                    ELIZABETH CAZOTTE.—MADEMOISELLE DE SOMBREUIL.—MADAME DE BOIS
                    BERANGER.—MADEMOISELLE DELLEGLACE.—INFANT VICTIM TO FILIAL AFFECTION.—THE CREOLE
                    AND HIS DAUGHTER.—MADAME DE ROCHEFOUCAULT. </p>
                <lb type="horBar"/>
                <div2>
                    <quote>"Heaven hath timely tried their youth, Their faith, their patience, and
                        their truth, And sent them here, through hard assays, With a crown of
                        deathless praise." <persName>M<hi rend="smallCaps">ilton</hi>.</persName>
                    </quote>
                    <p>N<hi rend="smallCaps">ature</hi> has implanted in every human breast a
                        disposition to love and revere the authors of our being, on whom, from our
                        earliest infancy, we are dependant for every comfort, convenience, and
                        pleasure in life: every heart which is not wholly destitute of feeling, must
                        beat with the warmest emotions of gratitude towards them, and be alive to
                        the tenderness of filial piety. Thus we find that in all ages of the world,
                        those who have become truly great, whatever may have been their country,
                        whether they have been the natives of enlightened <settlement
                            type="continent">Europe</settlement>, or of a <settlement
                            type="continent">land</settlement> of unpolished savages, have always
                        been distinguished, either in their <pb facs="noble_029.jpg" n="28"/>
                        <fw>28 FILIAL AFFECTION.</fw> infancy or at a more advanced period of life,
                        by some trait of this affection, which appears to form a basis for all the
                        other virtues.</p>
                </div2>
                <lb type="horBar"/>
                <div2>
                    <quote> "Can such things be, And overcome us like a summer's cloud, Without our
                        special wonder?" <persName>S<hi rend="smallCaps">hakespeare</hi>.</persName>
                    </quote>
                    <p>T<hi rend="smallCaps">he</hi> Roman history furnishes us with two remarkable
                        examples of filial piety. A Roman lady, of illustrious birth, had for some
                        cause been condemned to be strangled, and was sent to prison in order to be
                        put to death. The gaoler, who had received orders to strangle her, was
                        touched with compassion for her beauty and misfortunes, and not being able
                        to resolve to kill her, determined to let her die of hunger. He however
                        consented to allow her daughter to visit her in the prison, taking care that
                        she brought her mother no food. Many days elapsed, during which the
                        daughter's visits were very frequent: at length the gaoler became surprised
                        that his prisoner could exist so long without sustenance. His suspicions
                        immediately rested on the daughter, whom he now determined to watch still
                        more closely: to his utmost astonishment he found that she nourished her
                        mother with her own milk. His amazement at this pious and ingenious
                        invention caused him to inform the triumvir of the circumstance, who
                        immediately acquainted the praetor with it. The latter, <pb
                            facs="noble_030.jpg" n="29"/>
                        <fw>FILIAL AFFECTION. 29</fw> considering it worthy the public attention,
                        related it in an assembly of the people. The result was the pardon of the
                        criminal; and, at the same time, a decree was passed, that for the future
                        both mother and daughter should be supported at the public expense. The
                        Romans also raised a Temple upon the spot, and dedicated it to Filial
                        Piety.</p>
                </div2>
                <lb type="horBar"/>
                <div2>
                    <quote> "My child and father vital nurture crave, Parental, filial, fondness
                        both would save; But if a nursling only one can live, I choose to save the
                        life I cannot give." </quote>

                    <p>X<hi rend="smallCaps">antippe</hi>, another Roman lady, supported her aged
                        father Cimonus in a similar manner, in order to preserve his life while in
                        prison. This last circumstance was called the "Roman Charity." Both these
                        pious actions appeared so extraordinary to that people, that they could only
                        account for them by supposing that filial affection was the first law of
                        nature.</p>
                </div2>
                <lb type="horBar"/>
                <div2>
                    <quote> "'Twas the first time I mourned the dead: It was my heaviest loss, my
                        worst,— My father!—and was thine the first?" <persName>L. E.
                        L.</persName></quote>
                    <p>M<hi rend="smallCaps">odern</hi> history commemorates the name of Margaret
                        Roper, the daughter of Sir Thomas More, as another illustrious example of
                        this affection. When Sir Thomas, who had refused to take the oath of
                        supremacy, was cast into <pb facs="noble_031.jpg" n="30"/>
                        <fw>30 FILIAL AFFECTION. </fw> prison, his daughter, who was overwhelmed
                        with grief, was, through incessant importunity, permitted to visit him.
                        Admitted at length to his prison, she endeavoured, by every argument,
                        expostulation, and entreaty, to induce him to relent from his purpose. But
                        her eloquence, her tenderness, and her tears, were alike ineffectual:
                        constant to the last, the principles of this great and unfortunate man were
                        not to be shaken. Margaret corresponded with her father during the whole of
                        his imprisonment, and when deprived of pen and ink, Sir Thomas contrived to
                        write to her by means of a coal.</p>
                    <p>When sentence had been passed upon him, and he was returning towards the
                        Tower, Margaret rushed through the populace and the guards, and, without
                        speaking, threw her arms round her father's neck, clinging closely to him in
                        the stupor of despair. Even the guards melted into compassion at this
                        affecting scene. The fortitude of the noble prisoner seemed for a moment to
                        be shaken with the sight of his daughter's sorrow. Tenderly embracing her,
                        he withdrew himself from her arms. Scarcely however had he proceeded a few
                        paces further, when she again rushed towards him, and, in a paroxysm of
                        sorrow more eloquent than words, threw herself on his bosom. Tears flowed
                        while he down the venerable cheeks of Sir Thomas while he gazed upon her
                        with tender earnestness: having entreated her prayers for him, he bade her
                        affectionately farewell.</p>
                    <p>Margaret extended her cares to the lifeless <pb facs="noble_032.jpg" n="31"/>
                        <fw>FILIAL AFFECTION. 31</fw> remains of this beloved parent. Through her
                        interest and exertions, his body was, after his execution, interred in the
                        Chapel of St. Peter's <hi rend="italics">ad vincula</hi>, within the
                        precincts of the Tower: it was afterwards removed, according to the
                        appointment which had been made by Sir Thomas during his lifetime, to the
                        chancel of the church of Chelsea. His head, in conformity with the sentence,
                        having remained fourteen days exposed upon London Bridge, would have been
                        cast into the Thames, had it not been purchased by his daughter. Inhumanly
                        summoned in consequence before the council, Margaret firmly acknowledged and
                        justified her conduct. Such intrepidity could not escape King Henry's
                        vengeance: she was cast into prison, whence, after some vain attempts to
                        subdue her courage by menaces, she was permitted to escape, and join her
                        husband and family. At her death, which took place nine years after these
                        events, the head of her unfortunate parent was interred with her in her
                        arms, according to some historians; or, as others say, deposited in a leaden
                        box, and placed upon her coffin.</p>
                    <lb type="horBar"/>
                    <quote> "O glorious trial of exceeding, love, Illustrious evidence, example
                        high!" <persName>M<hi rend="smallCaps">ilton</hi>.</persName></quote>

                    <p>T<hi rend="smallCaps">he</hi> exile of the Bishop of Rochester gave occasion
                        to a very interesting exercise of paternal tenderness on the one part, and
                        of filial duty and affection on the other. What mostly <pb
                            facs="noble_033.jpg" n="32"/>
                        <fw>32 FILIAL AFFECTION.</fw> embittered the banishment of the Bishop, was
                        regret at leaving behind him his daughter, Mrs. Morice, in an infirm state
                        of health. A mutual longing to see one another took fast hold of the father
                        and daughter; and the lady, though very ill, performed, with great
                        difficulty and pain, a journey and voyage from <settlement type="city"
                            >Westminster</settlement> to <settlement type="city"
                            >Bourdeaux</settlement>, and <settlement type="city"
                            >Toulouse</settlement>, where Dr. Atterbury resided. Mr. J. Evans
                        accompanied Mr. and Mrs. Morice on their voyage from <settlement type="town"
                            >Dover</settlement> to <settlement type="city">Bourdeaux</settlement>,
                        and from thence to <settlement type="city">Toulouse</settlement>; and being
                        present at Mrs. Morice’s death, in a letter to his brother, dated
                        Montpelier, 30th November, 1729, gives the following very pathetic narrative
                        of that event.</p>
                    <q>"On Sunday, the 6th instant, N.S. in the evening, we reached <settlement
                            type="village">Blagnac</settlement>, a village not above half a league
                        by land from <settlement type="city">Toulouse</settlement>; but by water (by
                        reason of a very strong current, and the windings of the river,) it takes
                        three hours to get up to the town. So it was resolved, rather than expose
                        Mrs. Morice too much to the fatigue, (of which she had undergone an infinite
                        deal, and bore it with incredible patience,) or keep her late on the water,
                        to rest at <settlement type="village">Blagnac</settlement> that night, where
                        she was put to bed in the same weak condition she usually had been, but not
                        seemingly worse. About midnight, the women came to Mr. Morice and me, and
                        told us, they thought they saw her changed. We rose and came to her chamber,
                        when we found her so very ill, that we thought fit to call up the boatmen,
                        and order them to prepare the boat to depart immediately, fearing <pb
                            facs="noble_034.jpg" n="33"/>
                        <fw>FILIAL AFFECTION. 33 </fw> much, from the change we saw, that near she
                        was to it, she would scarcely live to reach <settlement type="city"
                            >Toulouse</settlement>, which we all earnestly desired to do, since no
                        physician, or other help, could be had in the poor place where we then were.
                        She herself pressed this matter; and we well knew that all her desires and
                        wishes were constantly bent upon seeing her father, whom she hoped to find
                        at <settlement type="city">Toulouse</settlement>. She was taken out of bed
                        at her own desire, and carried to the boat with great difficulty, not being
                        able to sit in the chair which Mr. Morice had brought from <settlement
                            type="city">Bourdeaux</settlement>, with two chairmen, purely for the
                        carrying her in and out of the boat more at ease; and so we parted thence
                        about two o'clock in the morning, sending two servants, by land, to procure
                        a litter to meet her at the by landing-place. About five we arrived there;
                        and soon after six the litter came, which carried Mrs. Morice to the house
                        in <settlement type="city">Toulouse</settlement>, where her father was
                        expecting her arrival, and not knowing, till then, how near or how far off
                        she was, though he had despatched a man and horse to get intelligence of us,
                        who happened to miss us. When the servants, who had been sent for the
                        litter, returned, she was informed of the Bishop's being at <settlement
                            type="city">Toulouse</settlement>, and seemed to take new spirits upon
                        it, which, no doubt, were of great use to enable her to bear going in the
                        litter, which, otherwise, she could scarce have done even for so short a
                        way. After she had been put into bed (where, as I told you, she never slept
                        till she slept her last,) and had a little recovered the fatigue she
                        underwent in <fw>VOL. I. D </fw>
                        <pb facs="noble_35.jpg" n="34"/>
                        <fw>34 FILIAL AFFECTION.</fw> the conveyance from the boat, which was about
                        a mile, her father, whom she immediately inquired after, came into her room,
                        and was startled to see her in so very low a condition. After mutual
                        expressions of concern and tenderness, she particularly acknowledged the
                        great blessing that was granted her, of meeting her dear papa; and exerted
                        all the little life that was in her, in grasping his hands with her utmost
                        force, as she often did; and told him, 'that meeting was the chief thing she
                        bad ardently desired.'</q>
                    <q>"The bishop some time after left her chamber, that she might compose herself,
                        and that he might give vent to the just grief he was filled with, to see his
                        beloved child in a manner expiring. But we found she took no rest: so he
                        soon returned, and then said prayers by her, and proposed to her receiving
                        the holy sacrament the next morning, when he hoped she might have been a
                        little refreshed, in order to it: she embraced the offer with much
                        satisfaction. He then asked her, for fear of any accident, if she was not
                        desirous to have the absolution of the church? She declared she was, and
                        begged to have it. After some little private discourse with her, he gave it
                        to her, in the form prescribed in 'The Visitation of the Sick,' and she
                        expressed great comfort of the fort upon receiving it. A physician had been
                        sent for immediately upon her arrival. When he came, he gave little hopes,
                        but said all depended upon her manner of passing that night.</q>
                    <q>"She once mentioned Dr. Wyntle, who you <pb facs="noble_036.jpg" n="35"/>
                        <fw>FILIAL AFFECTION. 35</fw> know had been her physician; and who had so
                        neglected her before she left <settlement type="country"
                            >England</settlement>, as never to come near her, according to his
                        appointment, nor give the least direction for her management in the long
                        voyage she was about to make. She said to the Bishop 'Dear papa, has Mr.
                        Morice told you how Dr. Wyntle has served us?' who answered, 'Yes, my dear,
                        I know it all; but do not let that trouble you now.' She replied, 'O no,
                        papa, I do not trouble myself about that I have other things to think of at
                        this time; but I did not know whether Mr. Morice had told you.'</q>
                    <q>"Hoping by this time she might incline to take a little rest, her father and
                        husband retired, it being between eleven and twelve at night; but about two
                        in the morning she sent one of her women to me, (who lay on the same floor,
                        in the next room to her,) to desire to speak to me; and when I came, she
                        said, not seemingly with much pain, but with such a shortness of breath that
                        she was forced to breathe after every two or three words, 'Mr. Evans, I have
                        been waking—these three hours—and would fain—have the sacrament.' I wondered
                        at her sending for me on that account, her husband and father being both
                        near at hand; but I found afterwards it was her unwillingness, by a direct
                        message from herself, too much to alarm either of them. However, being then
                        not apprized of her reason for it, I doubted a little of her being in her
                        right senses, and said, 'Madam, would you <hi rend="italics">now</hi>
                        receive the sacrament?' She said, 'Yes, I would, if possible—presently.' Of
                            <pb facs="noble_037.jpg" n="36"/>
                        <fw>36 FILIAL AFFECTION.</fw> which the Bishop being immediately advised, as
                        was Mr. Morice, and every thing being prepared, he came, and administered to
                        her, and to all present, the sacrament; and afterwards, at her desire,
                        continued repeating the prayers of the church, till she began to draw very
                        near her end, and then he used and continued the recommendatory prayer only;
                        she, all the while, holding her hands in a posture of prayer, and sometimes
                        joining in a low voice with him.</q>

                    <q>"After this, her father being gone from the bed-side, she called for him, (as
                        she had frequently done,) and again said to him, 'Dear papa—what a blessing
                        is it—that afer such a long—troublesome—journey—we have the comfort—of this
                        meeting!' And, indeed, when I reflect upon it, and consider the weak
                        condition she was in upon the road, the many accidents that happened to
                        retard the voyage, and the last effort she made, when she was at the worst,
                        think that that meeting seemed granted by heaven to her continued fervent
                        prayers for it.</q>
                    <q>"About this time she called for her husband, (who was always in near
                        attendance upon her,) and said, 'Dear Mr. Morice—take care of the children—I
                        know you will.—Remember me—to the Duchess of Buckingham.'</q>
                    <q>"She also, in a proper place, recommended her servants to Mr. Morice.</q>
                    <p>"She now found her feet cold, and ordered them to be rubbed, at the same time
                        calling for her broth; but when it came, not being able to <pb
                            facs="noble_038.jpg" n="37"/>
                        <fw>FILIAL AFFECTION. 37</fw> swallow it, she turned herself on her left
                        side, and rested her head on her left hand, which she doubled, extending her
                        right hand and arm over the bed-clothes; and in this posture continued
                        drawing her breath shorter and shorter, but with the least emotion that
                        possibly could be, till she at last expired, a quarter before four o'clock,
                        on Tuesday morning, 8th November, NS.</p>
                    <p>The following epitaph, written by Pope, on this striking example of
                        affection, is too interesting to be omitted here.</p>
                </div2>
                <div2>
                    <p>IS ATTERBURY, BISHOP OF ROCHESTER, —Who died in exile, at Paris, 1732, (his
                        only daughter having expired in his arms, immediately after she arrived in
                        France to see him.)</p>
                    <fw><hi rend="italics">Dialogue.</hi></fw>
                    <p><name type="pronoun">SHE.</name> Yes we have lived—one pang and then we part
                        ! May heaven, dear Father ! now have all thy heart ; Yet, ah ! how once we
                        lov'd, remember still, Till you are dust like me.</p>
                    <p><name type="pronoun">HE.</name> Dear shade ! I will Then mix this dust with
                        thine-0 spotless ghost ! 0 more than fortune, friends, or country lost! Is
                        there on earth one care, one wish beside, Yes—save my country,-heaven,— He
                        said and dy'd.</p>
                </div2>
                <lb type="horBar"/>
                <fw>D2</fw>
                <pb facs="noble_039.jpg" n="38"/>
                <fw>38 FILIAL AFFECTION.</fw>
                <div2>
                    <quote>"'Tis thine on ev'ry heart to grave thy praise, A monument which Worth
                        alone can raise.” <persName>B<hi rend="smallCaps"
                        >roome</hi>.</persName></quote>

                    <p>F<hi rend="smallCaps">rom</hi> the preceding illustrious sample of the power
                        of filial affection, we turn to one not less affecting, though displayed in
                        a humbler path of life. In the severe winter of 1783, Which was a time of
                        general distress at <settlement type="state">New York</settlement>, an aged
                        couple found themselves reduced to their last stick of wood. They had been
                        supported by the industry of a daughter who lived with them, but who now
                        found herself unable to procure them either fuel or provisions. Overcome
                        with grief at their destitute situation, she yet devised an expedient by
                        which they might be rescued from the emergency. She had accidentally heard
                        that a dentist had advertised or to give three guineas for every only sound
                        fore-tooth, provided only that he was allowed to extract it himself: the
                        generous girl, on remembering this, came to the resolution of disposing of
                        all her foreteeth, and went to the dentist for that purpose. On her arrival,
                        she made known the circumstances which had induced her to make so uncommon a
                        sacrifice.</p>
                    <p>Affected even to tears by the girl’s filial affection, the dentist refused to
                        avail himself of the offer, at the same time presenting her with ten
                        guineas, with which, her heart overflowing with joy and gratitude, she
                        hastened home to relieve her parents.</p>
                </div2>
                <lb type="horBar"/>
                <pb facs="noble_040.jpg" n="39"/>
                <fw>FILIAL AFFECTION. 39</fw>
                <div2>
                    <quote>"Stay, go, do what you will, the like do I; For live I will not, if my
                        father die." <persName>S<hi rend="smallCaps"
                        >hakespeare</hi>.</persName></quote>

                    <p>D<hi rend="smallCaps">uring</hi> the French Revolution, which endangered the
                        lives of so many parents, filial affection, rising superior to all selfish
                        considerations of safety, might be seen in many interesting forms. Daughters
                        then subjected themselves to every indignity, in their endeavours to
                        alleviate the sufferings of those who were dearer to them than life itself:
                        kneeling at the feet of their inhuman persecutors, they besought some
                        mitigation at least of their parents' sentence, and, if unsuccessful in
                        these efforts, shared their prison, and voluntarily partook their unhappy
                        fate.</p>

                    <p>Mademoiselle Cazotte, was an only child, and, at the commencement of the
                        Revolution, her father was seventy-two years of age. Closely connected with
                        La Porte (the intendant of the civil list), the fate of Cazotte was involved
                        in his. Some of Cazotte's letters being found on the person of La Porte, the
                        old man and his daughter were immediately arrested and sent to the prison of
                        the Abbey.</p>
                    <p>Shortly afterwards, Mademoiselle Cazotte having been pronounced innocent, an
                        order arrived at the prison that she might be set at liberty. Elizabeth
                        however refused to avail herself of it being resolved to share her father's
                        fate, and she succeeded in obtaining permission to remain with him. While in
                        and the prison, by her interesting appearance, and the pathetic eloquence of
                        her language, she was so fortunate <pb facs="noble_041.jpg" n="40"/>
                        <fw>40 FILIAL AFFECTION. </fw> as to interest some Marseillois, who had
                        quartered themselves in the Abbey, in her behalf; thus for a time her
                        father’s life was safe. On the 2d of September, however, after an
                        uninterrupted massacre, which had lasted three, hours, a number of voices
                        called loudly for Cazotte. At that name, which seemed to threaten instant
                        danger, Elizabeth rushed forward to meet her father's murderers. Her extreme
                        youth, wonderful beauty, and uncommon courage, seemed to shake their
                        purpose. One more stern and hardened in crime than the rest advanced to
                        Cazotte, and demanded why he had been imprisoned with his daughter. "You
                        will find it in the gaoler's book," was the old man's reply. Two of the
                        party being sent to examine the book, shortly returned with the tidings that
                        Cazotte was detained as a decided Counter-revolutionist. Scarcely was the
                        report uttered, when an axe was raised over the head of Cazotte. His
                        daughter, wildly shrieking, threw herself upon him, covering him with her
                        body, and disdaining to descend to unworthy supplications, only demanded to
                        die with him. " Strike, barbarians," she cried; "you cannot reach my father
                        but through my heart!" At this moving spectacle the assassins hesitated and
                        trembled, while a shout of pardon! Pardon! Was heard from one individual,
                        and echoed by a hundred voices. The Marseillois opened themselves a passage
                        to the two victims, and the father and daughter, covered with this sacred
                        shield, <pb facs="noble_042.jpg" n="41"/>
                        <fw>FILIAL AFFECTION. 41</fw> were conducted, with shouts of applause, from
                        that habitation of misfortunes and crimes.</p>
                    <p>The liberation of Cazotte, however, afforded temporary security: he was again
                        arrested upon the institution of the Criminal Tribunal. The good old man
                        endeavoured to dissuade his daughter from accompanying him to prison, but
                        his prayers, entreaties, and tears nay even his positive commands, were here
                        entirely fruitless. "In your company, my father" said Elizabeth, "I have
                        faced the most cruel of assassins; and shall I not be the companion of your
                        new misfortune, in which there is less danger? The hope of saving you will
                        again support me; I will show to your judges your forehead furrowed with age
                        I will ask them if a man, an old man, who has but a few days to linger out
                        among his fellow-beings, may not find mercy in the eyes of justice, after
                        having escaped the extreme of danger? If he, whose white hairs could plead
                        with assassins, ought not to receive indulgence from magistrates, one of
                        whose attributes should be mercy? The voice of nature will again be heard,
                        and perhaps I may again save you from the cruel fate which impends over us."
                        Overcome by her pressing entreaties Cazotte at last allowed his child to
                        attend him to the prison. When however they arrived there, the unhappy girl
                        was denied admission, and compelled to yield up her father. In an agony of
                        grief, she hastened to the Commune, and to the Minister of the Interior,
                        from whom, by her supplications and tears, she wrested their permission to
                        attend her <pb facs="noble_043.jpg" n="42"/>
                        <fw>42 FILIAL AFFECTION.</fw> father. From that moment she devoted he wholly
                        to him, spending day and night in administering to his comforts. The only
                        time that she passed away from his prison, was employed in securing promises
                        of support from the same <hi rend="italics">Marseillois</hi>, who had
                        formerly rendered her father such service; and she likewise, received
                        promises from several ladies of distinction, that their interest should be
                        exerted in her behalf. These expectations were, alas! vainly excited, for
                        every human being abandoned them in the hour of trial.</p>

                    <p>When Cazotte was called before the Tribunal the old man appeared, supported
                        by his daughter. A murmur of applause ran through the multitude that filled
                        the court at this affecting sight, while Elizabeth, with her eyes fixed on
                        her father, endeavoured to encourage and console him at this trying moment.
                        The pleading was soon commenced: during the reading of the written evidence,
                        and the speech of the Public Accuser, the entire feelings of Elizabeth were
                        imprinted on her beautiful countenance. Every one remarked the variety of
                        changes it underwent; fear and hope rapidly succeeding to each other:
                        several times she was on the point of raising her voice, but was checked by
                        remembering that her father had, previous to the trail, imposed silence on
                        her. At length she heard the dreadful conclusion of the speech of the Public
                        Accuser, which was but too faithful an omen of his fate. Pale, trembling,
                        and ready to sink into the ground, she was only sustained by her father’s
                        voice,</p>
                    <pb facs="noble_044.jpg" n="43"/>
                    <fw>FILIAL AFFECTION. 43</fw>
                    <p>Who in a low tone, pointing towards heaven, addressed to her a few words of
                        consolation. But though calmed for the moment, when the sentence was about
                        to be pronounced they found it necessary to remove her from the hall: and
                        when so far removed that her groans could no longer be heard, she abandoned
                        herself to a despair which baffles description. The unhappy girl had seen
                        her father for the last time: she had breathed a portion of her feelings
                        into every soul; and the deep sighs which arose from every corner of the
                        court, when she was carried thence, were proofs of the homage due to filial
                        virtue. Some humane persons followed her to the prison, where they found her
                        in a swoon: on recovering herself, she begged to be taken to her father,
                        that she might die with him. It was not until surrounded by her father's
                        friends, and become a witness of their affliction, that her own sorrow could
                        receive any mitigation, and the favourable moment was seized to lead her
                        back to her family.</p>
                </div2>
                <lb type="horBar"/>
                <div2>
                    <quote>"May my fears, My filial fears, be vain! and may the vaunts And menace of
                        the vengeful enemy Pass like the gust, thqt roar'd and died away In the
                        distant tree: which heard, and only heard in this low deli, bow'd not the
                        delicate grass!" <persName>C<hi rend="smallCaps"
                        >oleridge</hi>.</persName></quote>


                    <p>T<hi rend="smallCaps">he</hi> heroism of Elizabeth Cazotte, which could not
                        fail to excite the admiration and sympathy of her countrywomen, was imitated
                        by many young persons, from similar impulses <pb facs="noble_045.jpg" n="44"/>
                        <fw>44 FILIAL AFFECTION.</fw> Of devoted affection. Mademoiselle de
                        Sombreuil claims a share of our esteem for the intrepdity she displayed,
                        when, rushing into the presence of the murderers who had seized her father,
                        she exclaimed as she fell at their feet, "Barbarians, hold your hands—he is
                        my father!" In another moment she had so placed herself, that the sword
                        could not reach father but through the heart of his child. Perceiving that
                        they hesitated to accomplish their barbarous purpose, she supplicated once
                        more, with renewed earnestness, that they would spare her father's life.
                        Even while she spoke, one of the monsters, whose unfeeling heart was proof
                        against the self-devotion and heroism of the lovely girl at his feet,
                        annexed to her father's safety the following condition "Drink," said he, "a
                        glass of blood,-- and save your father." Mademoiselle de Sombreuil
                        shuddering, retreated several paces, but filial affection gained the
                        ascendance, and she yielded to the horrible proposal.</p>
                    <p>"Innocent or guilty then," said one of the judges who happened to be present,
                        "it is unworthy of the people to bathe their hands in the blood of this old
                        man, since they must first destroy this virtuous girl." A shout of "pardon!
                        Pardon!" was heard from those who had difficulty refrained from tears. The
                        daughter was clasped in her father’s trembling arms, and they left the
                        prison together, conducted in triumph by those who had come for so very
                        different a purpose.</p>
                    <p>Sombreuil had further evils to encounter: <pb facs="noble_046.jpg" n="45"/>
                        <fw>FILIAL AFFECTION. 45</fw> he was shortly again arrested with his
                        daughter, and led to prison. The latter had lost no portion of her courage,
                        though she had been afflicted with frequent convulsions since the violence
                        she had done to her feelings in drinking a glass of blood; and she displayed
                        each moment fresh proofs of her filial attachment. When the order for her
                        father’s trial arrived, although her heart was oppressed with the most
                        afflicting presages, she maintained an appearance of composure before her
                        parent, and to the last encouraged him to support himself with fortitude,
                        whatever might occur. Sombreuil finally yielded up his life on the scaffold,
                        when the existence of his daughter became a state worse than that of
                        death.</p>
                </div2>
                <lb type="horBar"/>
                <div2>
                    <quote>"The grave unites; where e'en the Great find rest, A nd blended lie th'
                        oppressor and th' opprest." <persName>P<hi rend="smallCaps"
                            >ope</hi>.</persName></quote>

                    <p>I<hi rend="smallCaps">n</hi> the prisons of <settlement type="city"
                            >Paris</settlement> whole families were frequently crowded together,
                        when the members of each would be united so strongly by sympathy that their
                        sole request and wish would be that they might die together, consoled by the
                        reflection, that in escaping from such scenes of dreadful persecution they
                        would still be united in a happier state of existence.</p>
                    <p> When the ci-devant marchioness de Bois Beranger was detained in the
                            <settlement type="country">Luxembourg</settlement> with her father,
                        mother, and a younger sister, she forgot her own misfortunes in indeavouring
                        to console her family under theirs. A soici- <fw>VOL. I. E </fw>
                        <pb facs="noble_047.jpg" n="46"/>
                        <fw>46 FILIAL AFFECTION.</fw> Tude even maternal was displayed in her
                        unceasing tenderness towards her mother, whose drooping fortitude was
                        re-animated by her example. When at length the act of accusation arrived for
                        her father, mother, and sister, Madame de Bois Beranger found that she alone
                        was exempt: and the discovery of the mournful preference filled her with
                        anguish. "You will die then," she exclaimed, "before me: and I am condemned
                        to survive you." Overwhelmed with despair, she clung to those beloved
                        relations, exclaiming, "Alas! Alas! We shall not die together!"</p>
                    <p>In the midst of this moving scene, a second accusation arrived at the prison,
                        in which the name of the marchioness was included. From this moment there
                        were no more tears, no more exclamations of grief from this affectionate
                        daughter. She flew to embrace her parents. "See," she cried, as she
                        displayed the act of accusation in joyful triumph, as though she held in her
                        hand the decree of their liberty and her own, "see my mother,--we shall die
                        together."</p>

                    <p>On the day of execution she attired herself with elegance, and cut off the
                        long tresses of her fine hair with her own hand. On leaving the Conciergerie
                        to go to the scaffold, she supported her mother, who seemed to be overcome
                        by an excess of grief. The sorrows of her parents appeared alone to be
                        subjects of regret tot eh marchioness at this critical moment. “Dearest
                        madam," she said in the tenderest accent, "be consoled: why are you not
                        happy? You <pb facs="noble_048.jpg" n="47"/>
                        <fw>FILIAL AFFECTION. 47</fw> die innocent, and in the same innocence all
                        your family follow you to the tomb, and will partake with you, in a better
                        state, the recompense of virtue."</p>
                </div2>
                <lb type="horBar"/>
                <div2>
                    <quote>"And is it then to live ? when such friends part, 'Tis the survivor
                        dies."</quote>

                    <p>M<hi rend="smallCaps">ademoiselle</hi> Delleglace was also a remarkable
                        instance of filial affection. When her father was to be conveyed from the
                        prison at <settlement type="city">Lyons</settlement> to the Conciergerie,
                        this affectionate girl, who from the first moment of his arrest never
                        quitted him, demanded permission to travel with him in the carriage prepared
                        for his journey. This boon she could not obtain; but what obstacles can
                        subdue the strength of filial love? Laying aside the timidity natural to her
                        sex, and wholly disregarding the weakness of her constitution, Mademoiselle
                        Delleglace set out on foot with the carriage, which she accompanied in that
                        manner for more than a hundred leagues. She sometimes quitted the side of
                        the carriage, but it was only when she preceded her father, to procure
                        proper nourishment for him in the towns through which they passed; and in
                        the evening of every day, when she ran forward to beg of some charitable
                        person a covering, to administer to her father's wants, in the dungeon where
                        he must pass the night.</p>

                    <p>When at length they reached the gates of the Conciergerie, she was denied
                        admittance with him, and compelled to give up the expec- <pb
                            facs="noble_049.jpg" n="48"/>
                        <fw>48 FILIAL AFFECTION.</fw> tation of being his companion in prison. But
                        her fortitude did not yet give way: she did not cease, during three months,
                        to implore the justice and humanity of all those influential persons to whom
                        she could gain access, perseverance was finally crowned with success; and
                        exulting with joy, she hastened to bear the happy tidings to her father, and
                        contemplated the delight of herself conducting him back to his home and
                        family. But it was otherwise ordained: worn out by the excess of fatigue she
                        had undergone during this unparalleled exertion, she was taken ill on the
                        road and obliged to remain at an inn, until her father could be informed of
                        the circumstance and be set at liberty. She never again left her bed, but
                        died in her beloved parent's arms; still deeming herself happy in having
                        purchased his life at the expense of her own.</p>
                </div2>
                <lb type="horBar"/>
                <div2>
                    <quote>"O'er friendless grief compassion shall awake, And smile on innocence,
                        for mercy's sake." <persName>C<hi rend="smallCaps"
                        >ampbell</hi>.</persName></quote>

                    <p>W<hi rend="smallCaps">ho</hi> has not heard, and who has not shed tears at
                        hearing, of that beautiful and interesting girl of only eight years of age,
                        who went every morning to the <settlement type="city" subtype="square">Place
                            de la Revolution</settlement>, to mourn and lament the death of her
                        mother, who was executed there? The child took many precautions to escape
                        observation; but her manner was at length noticed by some women who sold
                        fruit near the spot. Being asked the cause of her tears, "Ah!" she said, <pb
                            facs="noble_050.jpg" n="49"/>
                        <fw>FILIAL AFFECTION. 49</fw> "my poor mother, whom I loved so well, died
                        where I now stand; but oh! do not, I beg of you, tell anyone that you saw me
                        cry, for that, perhaps, would cause the death of my brother and my sisters."
                        After this guileless answer, which greatly effected her audience, she
                        hastily retired, and was never seen there again. It was afterwards known
                        that this early victim of filial affection died in a few weeks, bowed down a
                        grief which she could not cast off."</p>
                </div2>
                <lb type="horBar"/>
                <div2>
                    <quote>"What breast so cold, that is not warmed here?" <persName>S<hi
                                rend="smallCaps">hakespeare</hi></persName>,</quote>
                    <p>A<hi rend="smallCaps">nother</hi> child was the happy means of saving her
                        father's life. He was a Creole of <settlement type="city">St.
                            Domingo</settlement>, and was guilty of no other crime than that of
                        being rich and preserving the inheritance of his forefathers. At that time
                        when the contagious example of the French revolution had spread as far as
                        the New World, the horrible practice was adopted of assembling in groupes
                        the unfortunate victims who were ordered to be executed, and then firing l
                        indiscriminately upon them with cannons loaded with grape-shot. The eyes of
                        the Creole had been blindfolded, and he stood among a crowd of other
                        unfortunate beings, expecting every instant the signal of death. When,
                        however, the order to discharge artillery was about to be given, a little
                        girl rushed forward, with a loud cry of "My <pb facs="noble_051.jpg" n="50"/>
                        <fw> 50 FILIAL AFFECTION. </fw> "father! Oh my father! And making her way
                        through the victims, threw her little arms about her parent’s neck, and
                        waited for the moment of dying with him. In vain were all the threats of
                        entreaties; neither the representations of her danger, nor the commands of
                        her father could intimidate her. In reply to the latter, she earnestly
                        repeated, "Oh! My father, let me die with you." What power has virtue over
                        the most ferocious minds! This unexpected accident disconcerted the
                        commander of the massacre:--doubtless he was a father too! The voice of
                        admiration and exclamations of pity, which he heard from all sides, touched
                        his heart, and under some specious pretext, the Creole was delivered from
                        the expected punishment, and, accompanied by his child, reconducted to
                        prison; whence he soon afterwards obtained his release. After that happy
                        escape, he was often accustomed to relate, with feelings of tender emotion,
                        the heroic action of his little girl, then only ten years of age.</p>
                </div2>
                <lb type="horBar"/>
                <div2>
                    <quote>"Such is my love, to thee I so belong, That for thy right, myself will
                        bear all wrong." <persName>S<hi rend="smallCaps">hakespeare</hi></persName>. </quote>

                    <p>D<hi rend="smallCaps">uring</hi> the war of La Vendee, the ci-devant Duke de
                        la <settlement type="commune">Rochefoucault</settlement>, condemned to die,
                        as well as his daughter, found in the resources of that affectionate girl
                        the means of concealing himself until a period arrived more favourable to
                        that justice which he unsuccessfully claimed.</p>
                    <pb facs="noble_052.jpg" n="51"/>
                    <fw>FILIAL AFFECTION. 51</fw>
                    <p>His daughter's first care was to place him under the roof and protection of
                        an artisan, who had formerly been a domestic in the duke's service, after
                        which she procured an asylum for herself. They were thus both secure from
                        the immediate power of their persecutors; but, as the duke’s property was
                        confiscated, and compassion is apt to grow weary of its good offices, the
                        means of their bare subsistence were soon exhausted. While the daughter was
                        suffering under the extreme of poverty, she learnt that her father's health
                        was rapidly declining for want of due nourishment. Madame de la <settlement
                            type="commune">Rochefoucault</settlement> now saw but one resource left
                        : to devote her own life to save that of her father ; and she instantly
                        resolved upon the sacrifice.</p>
                    <p>A general of the <settlement type="country" subtype="france"
                            >Republic</settlement> happened at that time to be passing through the
                        city in which was her place of concealment: she addressed the following
                        letter to hi : "C<hi rend="smallCaps">itizen</hi> G<hi rend="smallCaps"
                            >eneral</hi>: Wherever the voice of nature is heard, a daughter may be
                        allowed to claim the compassion of men in behalf of her father. Condemned to
                        death at the same time with him who Gave me being, I have successfully
                        preserved him from the sword of the executioner, and have preserved myself
                        to watch over his safety. But in saving his life, I have not been able to
                        furnish all that is necessary to support him. My unhappy father, whose
                        entire property is confiscated, suffers at this moment the want of almost
                        every thing. Without clothes, without bread, without a <pb
                            facs="noble_053.jpg" n="52"/>
                        <fw>52 FILIAL AFFECTION.</fw> Friend to save him from perishing of want, he
                        has not even the resource of the beggar, which still furnishes a little
                        hope, that of being able to appeal to the compassionate, and to present his
                        white hairs to those that might be moved to give him aid: my father, if he
                        is not speedily succoured, will die in his place of concealment, and thus,
                        after snatching him from a violent death, I shall have to sustain the
                        mournful reflection of having betrayed him to one more lingering and
                        painful—that of dying of cold and hunger.</p>
                    <p>"Be the judge, Citizen General, of the extent of my misfortune, and own that
                        it is worthy of pity. One resource only is left to me: it is to cast myself
                        upon your generosity. I offer you my head: I undertake to go, and to go
                        willingly, to the scaffold; but give immediate succor to my dying father.
                        Below I give you the name of my place of concealment, there I will expect
                        death with pleasure, if I may promise myself that you will be touched with
                        my prayers, and will relieve my old and destitute parent."</p>

                    <p>The soldier had no sooner read this letter, than he hastened to the asylum of
                        Madame de <settlement type="commune">Rochefoucault</settlement>, and not
                        only relieved her father, but secretly protected both, and finally produced
                        the restoration of M. de <settlement type="commune"
                            >Rochefoucault</settlement>’s property by a revision of their
                        sentence.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
